Farewell, Earth
The ship that is departing is
The Space Battleship
Yamato
It departs now to Iscandar,
at the end of the cosmos,
bearing its fate.
"We will come back, no matter what it takes"
Answer with a smile to the waving people
Going far from the Galaxy towards Iscandar
A faint gleam of hope
The Space Battleship Yamato
Today, on Yamato Radio Theater,
Someone calling themselves Shiro Shinta has requested
one of the famous late 21st century stories,
"The Heart of Observer #9."
Back when there were still no towns on Mars,
a single observation station stood alone, at the edge of Mare Sirenum.
No one ever visited this forgotten tower,
where a single, young observer lived like a lighthouse keeper.
He had no name, only the number "9."
A Clockwork Parable
Transferring visual sensors from Garmiroid A to Garmiroid B.
It worked.
All three Garmiroid soldiers we recovered on Enceladus
were automata with orthodox AIs.
Automata?
Mechanical dolls, right?
By running a massive number of simple programs in parallel,
it can perform complex actions just like humans do.
They share the same fundamental architecture as our artificial intelligences.
So we know Garmillas uses the same mathematics
and understanding of physics that we do.
Their culture should be one we can communicate with.
When you encounter a foreign civilization in space, this is very important.
Especially in times of war.
It lets us play shogi by the same rules.
I see.
Did we manage to salvage any other information?
Such as enemy positions?
Well, two of their storage units were too badly damaged for repair.
The other's survived, but the data is only accessible from a Garmillas mainframe.
But then...
However, there is a way.
Have the Garmiroid tell us.
Mainframe restored.
Rebooting Garmiroid Alternative.
Can you hear me?
I am Type AU09, the sub-frame of this ship.
Please call me Analyzer.
A... A-An... An-Analyzer?
You are a rebooted, alternative version of a foreign civilization's servant android.
I know... I'll call you Alter!
Alter...
Warp complete.
No enemies in immediate vicinity.
Sanada, I will return to analyzing Alter.
Go ahead.
Right!
Analyzer appears to be enjoying himself.
I'm sure he is.
He has another machine to talk to.
What is this?
A cat.
No, no. This is a dog.
Dogs are mammals.
Mammals are animals.
Mammal. Animal.
Then what is this?
A dog.
No, this is a cat.
Oh, Analyzer. Are you two machines having a secret chat?
Nothing of the sort.
I am teaching Alter to speak.
To speak, huh?
You were able to link operating systems, so just import the dictionary data.
The names alone are not enough.
To understand a concept, large numbers of exchanges are required.
And...
That's true.
You can't connect it to the ship's network.
I was right. We didn't investigate enough.
This doesn't tell me if we can colonize it.
Do Automata Dream of Electric Sheep?
One day, an old mechanical engineer named Houdin
appeared at the observatory with a girl named Eve.
The meeting was magical.
Following the sound of a song to the sea,
#9 saw a girl sitting on a rock, singing.
"Wh-Who?"
She turned and asked,
"Who are you?"
"What are you doing out here?"
I met a goddess yesterday.
A goddess?
The goddess of this ship.
Who might that be?
They asked, "Who are you?"
And I replied, "I am Alter."
And they said, "I am not asking for your name."
Operations Officer Mori, perhaps?
Or Miss Niimi?
No, that's impossible.
Can you answer it?
Who are you?
I am...
This is Shinohara.
I'm investigating the spatial wake in front of us.
I've confirmed that it's safe.
Roger.
Shinohara and Yamamoto
completing patrol and returning to ship.
When both have returned,
we will move to warp navigation at 0200.
Roger.
Prepare for docking.
Analyzer, give them a hand, okay?
Roger.
I win.
They're back.
Let's go.
No fair! I had a straight flush!
Navi, handle the automatic docking guidance for me.
Switching to automatic control.
Thanks, Navi.
Just now, you were thinking that I'm nuts, weren't you?
I was not.
Name them, take care of them, and they'll do good work for you.
Exactly like anyone else.
Open hatch, port side.
Okay, let's get started.
Guidance team, prepare to pull them in.
Okay, okay!
Alter?
Toyama, is there an error on the control panel?
The monitor's down.
What?
Force purge!
Purging-
What the heck?!
Toyama!
Shinohara!
I'm on it!
What's wrong with you?
What were you thinking?
Um, well... I really don't know what happened.
That crane's movements are controlled by a program, right?
Yes, they are.
But for some reason, the system monitor went down today.
Normally, they should shut down automatically.
This has never happened.
You morons!
Just because it's never happened before
doesn't mean it won't happen today!
Why do you think we have humans there to help the machines?
Yes, sir.
I'm sorry, both of you.
Forgive us.
No... I mean, you're taking it seriously...
Right?
Y-Yes.
Before the accident, you were talking to Alter via network, weren't you?
Yes.
There was a very minor delay in the
process that feeds hangar information
back to the mainframe.
That caused the arm malfunction.
I'm terribly sorry.
Your conversations with Alter may be stressing the system unexpectedly.
Should this keep happening, I'll have to reformat you.
That would be...
...the correct decision.
We're done analyzing Alter for a while.
You're forbidden from coming here or speaking to Alter via network.
We'll keep an eye on things for now.
Got it?
Yes, sir.
The old man sent Eve back, on board the ship.
And the observer desired nothing more than to see her again.
For the first time in his life, he understood loneliness.
He decided to go and see Eve.
He felt that this was the only way to learn who he was.
I, Robot
Sanada, I learned something from talking with Alter.
They are just like me.
I see.
Alter asked me who I am.
What did you tell him?
A friend.
A friend, huh?
Good answer.
Where is the goddess?
What has happened?
Apparently, the lock to the analysis room has been destroyed.
That Garmiroid...
Send security at once!
Weapons approved, where appropriate!
Ship has moved to Alert Status 1.
Repeat: Ship has moved to Alert Status 1.
The Garmiroid we recovered has escaped the analysis room.
It is hiding somewhere aboard the ship.
Security teams are to capture or destroy it.
Is that it?
Repeat: Security teams are to capture or destroy it.
Stop!
Don't move. Stay right there.
Target acquired!
It's fleeing on the port side deck 3!
Alter wanted to know who he was.
He must think if he finds the goddess, he will learn.
The goddess?
Alter said she was the goddess of this ship.
And I learned one other important thing about the Garmiroids...
Don't let him escape. Seal the bulkheads.
Don't move!
Mori, where is the Garmiroid soldier?
Heading straight toward the ship's bow, via the deck 2 ducts.
We're heading toward the sealed room, aren't we?
It contains the automatic guidance systems to take us to Iscandar.
Is that his objective?
There he is!
Don't let him reach it! Destroy him if you must!
Enemy...
Terror...
Being...
Goddess!
The Garmiroid has entered the second turret loading room.
Flow My Tears, the Automata Said
Well?
No good. It's locked from the inside.
Bridge, get that lock open!
As soon as it opens, we fire.
This is the bridge.
He's infiltrated our security and locked it from the inside.
It will take some time to unlock it.
Please stand by.
Perfect timing, AU09. Open the door.
Before that, put your guns away.
What?
I don't want him to think we're enemies.
What are you talking about? Of course we're enemies.
Will you kill an unresisting prisoner?
Misaki?
A prisoner?
That's stupid.
It's just a robot.
If it has a heart, even a machine should be treated as a prisoner.
A heart? It has a heart?
I was told it was an automaton.
That's what the XO said.
It's true that the Garmiroids
are automata that function by running massive numbers of programs.
Correct? Machines are just machines.
But we cannot say for certain that our brains
are not also automata that function via parallel processing.
It seems you want to believe that
their processing circuitry cannot give rise to a consciousness like ours.
However, you cannot actually prove that that's the case.
An interesting story.
I've retaken control of the security.
Anyway, for the moment, put away your weapons.
If you say so, XO.
The door will open.
Misaki?
Sanada, I recommend that Alter be shut down immediately.
Why is that?
Alter may commit suicide.
He is programmed to self-destruct if isolated and surrounded by enemies.
Stop him!
Analyzer, let's go.
XO Sanada.
You don't think it has a heart, do you?
To me, it remains unclear whether even you have a heart.
It may be that you don't have a heart like I do.
You could just be simulating a human.
The Garmiroid soldier has exited the ship.
It's moving along the upper deck, toward the bridge.
Don't allow it to get near the automatic guidance system.
We will destroy it if we must.
Shell block destroyed.
Infiltrating kernel.
Dog.
Cat.
Being.
Goddess.
Death.
Fr... ie... n... d...
Garmiroid Alternative has been shut down.
Mainframe has been reformatted and cannot be rebooted.
Recover its task log.
Roger.
The analysis is complete.
We found nothing in Alter's task log to indicate an activated booby trap.
Then...
Yes.
If nothing else, he believed he still had at least one friend on this ship.
The Heart of Observer #9
Eve's skin was peeled away, her joints torn off,
revealing a body of gears and silicon.
From the tower's window, #9 watched her sink into the Mare Sirenum.
"I no longer feel pity for that doll.
Because I know that I am also one, created by Houdin,"
he thought to himself, alone in his
small room in the observation station.
Whether that beautiful doll did or did not have a heart,
it didn't matter to him.
And he thought this, as well...
"The fact that I have a heart
is a secret that belongs only to me."
Episode 9
Clockwork Prisoner
That girl was waving
A bright red scarf
Who do you think it was for?
Whoever it was
It doesn’t matter
Let each think it was for him
The hearts of men beginning a journey
Want a piece of romance
A bright red scarf
The Yamato plunges through a
dimensional gap, into a ship's graveyard.
A cruel space, devoid of life.
And there, the shadow of an enemy ship appears.
Will they work together or against one other?
Will men be able to work together, rather than wait for death?
Next time: Graveyard of the Universe.
There are 325 days left before humanity is extinct.